Guide to the Cornwall Miscellanea 1779-2003 MS 011 MS 011 MS 011
Cornwall Historical Society
- Photographic Materials
  - Photographs
    - Locations
      - Cream Hill
        - Scoville Road, circa 1870-1989 (Box 19, Folder 1)
          Photographs taken of various properties along Scoville Road. Specific images include the Benton-Chapin House at the corner of Scoville Road and Cream Hill Road and a photograph of the Scoville farmhouse taken by the Pease Brothers of Lee, Mass.
        - Rexford House, N.D. (Box 19, Folder 2)
          Photographs of the Rexford House. The property was later owned by the Hubbard and Sureda families.
        - Cream Hill Lake Part I, 1901-2001 (Box 19, Folder 3)
          Photographs of Cream Hill Lake. One group of photographs features images of the lake itself, while the other shows properties that stood along the shore. Specific cottages include the Laurel Lodge, the Nutshell, Echo Rocks, the "Old Club House," the old boat house, and the Cochrane Camp.
        - Cream Hill Lake Part II, 1901-1989 (Box 19, Folder 4)
          Photographs of various Cornwall residents at Cream Hill Lake taking part in activities such as swimming, boating, and tennis. Specific people include Edward Cartwright, David Mason, Harry Sedgwick, J.A. Cochrane, Mrs. E.C. Starr, Mrs. George Woolsey, and Mrs. John E. Calhoun.
        - Landscapes, 1889-1989 (Box 19, Folder 5)
          Photographs of various landscapes taken in and around Cream Hill.
        - Senzer House, 1989 (Box 19, Folder 6)
          Photograph of the Senzer House on Cogswell Road.
        - Simmons House, circa 1990 (Box 19, Folder 7)
          Photograph of the old Simmons House on Cogswell Road. The structure was torn down in the early 1990s.
        - Van Valkenburgh House, N.D. (Box 19, Folder 8)
          Photographs of the Van Valkenburgh family home.
        - Hubbard/Cain Farm, circa 1920 (Box 19, Folder 9)
          Photograph of the Hubbard/Cain farm house on Cream Hill Road.
        - Hart Farm, 1869-1904 (Box 19, Folder 10)
          Photographs of the Hart family farm. Specific images include photos of the farm house and of the mail being delivered.
        - Miscellaneous, N.D. (Box 19, Folder 11)
          Photographs of unlabeled people and structures in Cream Hill.
        - Yelping Hill Association, January 1995 (Box 19, Folder 12)
          Photograph of the Yelping Hill Association barn.
        - Yelping Hill, circa 1920-1962, N.D. (Box 21, Folder 25)
          Photographs from Yelping Hill. Images include photos of the Dodd and Smith homes as well as scenes of play rehearsals and people swimming.
      - Cornwall Plain
        - Baldwin House, N.D. (Box 19, Folder 13)
          Photograph of the T.R. Baldwin House.
        - Bolton Hill Road, circa 1900-circa 2000 (Box 19, Folder 14)
          Photographs of various properties located on Bolton Hill Road. Specific images include photos of the parsonage and the Northrop House.
        - Calhoun Farm, N.D. (Box 19, Folder 15)
          Photographs of the Calhoun family farm on Jewell Street. Photos include images of the J.E. Calhoun farm house and several Calhoun barns.
        - The Cornwall Castle, 1980-1988 (Box 19, Folder 16)
          Photographs of the Cornwall Castle property. Specific images include artisans at work in the property's pottery shop and images of the building's renovation in the 1980s.
        - Cathedral Pines, 1906-1979, N.D. (Box 19, Folder 17)
          Photographs of the Cathedral Pines. The stand of old-growth hemlock and white pine trees was donated to the Nature Conservancy in 1967 by the Calhoun family. Much of the area was destroyed by tornadoes in 1989. Many images focus on the "Tree on the Rock."
        - First Church, 1953-circa 2000, N.D. (Box 19, Folder 18)
          Photographs of the United Church of Christ near the village green. The congregation was first organized in 1741, and the current structure was built in 1842.
        - Village Green, 1889-circa 2000, N.D. (Box 19, Folder 19)
          Photographs of the Cornwall village green. Specific images include photos of the Charter Oak scion and the Cornwall Honor Roll.
        - Marsh Carriage House/ Cornwall Historical Society, 1927-circa 2000, N.D. (Box 19, Folder 20)
          Photographs of the former Marsh carriage house on Pine Street. The structure originally belonged to J.T. Andrews and was purchased by the Marsh family circa 1890. The building was converted into the residence of town historian Emily E. Marsh in 1954 and opened as the new home of the Cornwall Historical Society in 1967. Specific images include J.T. Andrews posing in front of his barn, as well as photos of the building when it served as both a private residence and as the historical society.
        - Jewell Street, 1890-circa 2000, N.D. (Box 19, Folder 21)
          Photographs of various properties located along Jewell Street. Specified images include the Dunn House and the residence of town historian, Rev. E.C. Starr.
        - Kellogg House, circa 1930-1956, N.D. (Box 19, Folder 22)
          Photographs of the Kellogg House on Valley Road. Photos include images of both the interior and exterior of the home. An image donated by Bessie Kellogg depicts her mother Maria Kellogg posing in front of the building.
        - Landscapes, circa 1890-circa 1970, N.D. (Box 19, Folder 23)
          Photographs of various landscapes from around Cornwall Plain. Specific images include the Ballyhack and an old stone dam built by Joel Bunnell (1769-1854).
        - St. Peter's Lutheran Church, 1966-circa 2000 (Box 19, Folder 24)
          Photographs of St. Peter's Lutheran Church on Bolton Hill Road. The building originally served as a chapel for the nearby First Church.
          - Lutheran Church, N.D. (Box OS 3, Folder 9)
            Black-and-white photo of the Lutheran Church.
        - Valley Road, N.D. (Box 20, Folder 1)
          Photographs of various properties along Valley Road. Specific images include the Alfred Bacon Home and the house formerly owned by Frank Calhoun.
        - Machado House, circa 1940-1987 (Box 20, Folder 2)
          Photographs of the Machado House. Later owned by the Tennant family.
        - Marsh Houses, 1920-circa 2000, N.D. (Box 20, Folder 3)
          Photographs of two houses owned by the Marsh family. The Cyrus C. Marsh home was built circa 1785 and later remodeled in the Queen Ann style in 1903. The second Marsh home was built circa 1865 by Cyrus William Marsh and later owned by Helen Tausley.
        - Post Office, 1984 (Box 20, Folder 5)
          Photographs of the post office building on Bolton Hill Road.
        - Town Offices/Library, 1953-1980, N.D. (Box 20, Folder 6)
          Photographs of the Cornwall town offices. The core building originally served as a library. Specific images include an addition built in 1976 and a vault designed by T. Merrill Prentice.
        - Route 4, N.D. (Box 20, Folder 7)
          Photographs of various structures along the section of Route 4 that passes through Cornwall Plain. Specific images include the Edith Woolsey house built circa 1854.
        - School Street, N.D. (Box 20, Folder 8)
          Photographs of unlabeled properties along School Street. Images include photos of an unspecified structure fire.
        - Pine Street, N.D.
          Photographs of unspecified properties along Pine Street.
        - Pine Street Part II, 1900-1995, N.D. (Box 20, Folder 10)
          Photographs of the Pine Street area. Images include photos of the street itself and residences along its route. Specific buildings include the T.R. Baldwin House, the Henry Cole House, the Stephen J. Gold House, the MacLean House, the Rev. Timothy Stone House, and the Colin Wilcox House.
        - Wilcox Store, N.D. (Box 20, Folder 11)
          Photographs of the C.E. Wilcox and Son store building that stood near the village green. Images include a photo donated by Ralph and Myron Corban.
        - Miscellaneous, N.D. (Box 20, Folder 13)
          Photographs of various properties in Cornwall Plain. The sole labeled structure being the Benjamin Gray House.
        - Aftermath of 1989 Tornado (Box 35, Folder 27)
          Photographs of the destruction following the 1989 tornado. Specific images include a photograph of Todd Hill Road taken an hour after the storm, and photos of the Cathedral Pines.
        - Coltsfoot Valley, June 16, 1988 (Box 35, Folder 30)
          Photograph of Coltsfoot Valley.
        - First Church Steeple Repair, January 3, 1980 (Box 35, Folder 33)
          Photograph of Calvin Flint and his son Ray Flint bracing the trusses of the First Church steeple.
        - Aftermath of 1989 Tornado, July 1989, N.D. (Box 35, Folder 27)
          Photographs of tornado damage in Cornwall Plain, including the damage to the Cathedral Pines.
        - Coltsfoot Valley, June 16, 1988 (Box 35, Folder 30)
        - Meeting House Steeple Repair, January 3, 1980 (Box 35, Folder 33)
          Photograph of Ray and Calvin Flint working in the steeple of the Congregational Church.
        - Bear Swamp Brook Dam, October 1969 (Box OS 3, Folder 16)
          Photograph of a dam built by Joel Bunnell near the Crooked Esses around 1870. Photo taken by Armin Landeck.
      - East Cornwall
        - Baldwin House, N.D. (Box 20, Folder 14)
          Photograph of the Badlwin family home with an unknown individual posing in the yard.
        - Clark Homestead, 1957-1993, N.D. (Box 20, Folder 15)
          Photographs of the former Clark homestead, also known as Mohawk Farms. Specific images include photos of Mary Lydia Clark's birthday and an auction held at the homestead by Harriet L. Clark in October 1993.
          - Clark Homestead, N.D. (Box OS 3, Folder 8)
            Photographs of the Clark property in East Cornwall.
        - Clark Road, N.D. (Box 20, Folder 16)
          Photograph of an unspecified portion of Clark Road.
        - Clark/Skiff House, N.D. (Box 20, Folder 17)
          Photograph of the Clark/Skiff House with individuals standing in the yard.
        - Dean/Clark House, September 1942 (Box 20, Folder 18)
          Photograph of the Dean/Clark House taken by R.S. Myers.
        - Baptist Church/Ripley House, 1976, N.D. (Box 20, Folder 19)
          Photographs of the former East Cornwall Baptist Church which stood at the corner of South Street and Flat Rocks Road. One photo donated by H. Clark depicts the annual visit to the church by Reverend Fennell known as "Fennell Sunday." The other photo shows the home Louis Ripley built on the church's foundation after the structure was demolished.
        - Great Hill Road, 1957, N.D. (Box 20, Folder 20)
          Photograph of the area along Great Hill Road known as Koehler's Corner. Photo donated by Priscella Rogers.
        - Great Hollow Road, 1888-1930, N.D. (Box 20, Folder 21)
          Photographs of properties along Great Hollow Road. Specific images include the now-gone Oliver Chipman House, the former home of Virginia Smith, the High Bridge, and photos of the Corban family farm.
        - Kellogg Farm, N.D. (Box 20, Folder 22)
          Photographs of the Kellogg family farm on Great Hollow Road. Specific images include photos of the farm house and livestock.
        - Armin Landeck House, 1972-circa 2000, N.D. (Box 20, Folder 23)
          Photographs of the Armin Landeck House on Great Hill Road. The home was formerly occupied by Charlotte Clark Pikowsky.
        - Mohawk Mountain Ski Area, 1960-1989, N.D. (Box 20, Folder 24)
          Photographs of the Mohawk Mountain Ski Area on Great Hollow Road. Specific images include photos donated by John "Denny" Frost.
        - Phelps Place, 1997 (Box 20, Folder 25)
          Photograph of the Phelps House.
        - Seeley Road, N.D. (Box 20, Folder 26)
          Photograph of a dwelling along Seeley Road formerly owned by the Hart, Baker, and Finch families, respectively.
        - Philander Vaill Home (Box 20, Folder 27)
          Photograph of Philander Vaill (1803-1895) in front of his home near the top of Bunker Hill. The house was built in 1839.
        - Former Mohawk Mountain Homesteads, 1912-1938, N.D. (Box 20, Folder 28)
          Photographs of farmsteads that formerly stood in Mohawk Mountain State Park. Specific images include the Strattmann House in various stages of decay, the Hart Farm, and a marker at the site of the Leavitt Clark Homestead.
        - Mohawk Mountain Civilian Conservation Corps., 1933 (Box 20, Folder 29)
          Photographs of Camp Toumey, the camp used by the Civilian Conservation Corps members who worked in Cornwall during the Great Depression. The camp opened on Mohawk Mountain in 1933 and remained in operation until 1941.
        - Camp Mohawk, 1920-1925, N.D. (Box 20, Folder 30)
          Photographs of Camp Mohawk. The camp opened in 1920 and stood near the shore of Mohawk Pond. Specific images include photos of campers swimming, eating, and attending outdoor church services.
        - Mohawk Mountain State Forest, 1936-1941, N.D. (Box 20, Folder 31)
          Photographs from Mohawk Mountain State Park. Specific images include photos of rock formations taken by E.C. Starr, the Cunningham Tower, Mohawk Tower, and a photograph of a group of forest rangers.
        - Perkins House, 1937 (Box 20, Folder 32)
          Photograph of the Perkins family farm house.
        - Blake House, 1981 (Box 20, Folder 33)
          Photograph of the Blake House.
        - Landscapes, circa 2000 (Box 20, Folder 34)
          Photographs of various landscapes in East Cornwall. Images were all taken along roadways.
        - Miscellaneous, 1888-circa 2000 (Box 20, Folder 35)
          Photographs of assorted properties in East Cornwall. Labeled images include a photo of the William Major Home and a muddy section of road near the Warren Welch Home.
        - Clark Homestead, 2000 (Box 20, Folder 36)
          Photographs of the vacant Clark homestead.
        - Mohawk Mountain Ski Area, 1951-1955, N.D. (Box 35, Folder 22)
          Photographs of people skiing at Mohawk Mountain.
        - Mohawk Mountain Chairlifts, 1993 (Box 35, Folder 31)
          Photographs of cyclists riding the chairlifts at Mohawk Mountain.
      - Cornwall Hollow
        - Baptist Church, circa 1900-1989 (Box 21, Folder 1)
          Photographs of the Cornwall Hollow Baptist Church. The church opened in 1844 and was converted into a private home in the twentieth century. One photo, donated by Helen Blake Smith, shows the building while still in use as a church. The others depict the building as a private residence.
        - Bradford House, N.D. (Box 21, Folder 2)
          Copy of a photograph of the Bradford family homestead. The farm house was built circa 1798 by John Bradford.
        - Dodd House, N.D. (Box 21, Folder 3)
          Photograph of the house owned by Ed Dodd on Fox Road.
        - Ben Foster House, circa 1900 (Box 21, Folder 4)
          Photograph of the Ben Foster House donated by Robert Austin.
        - Johnson House, N.D. (Box 21, Folder 5)
          Photographs of the exterior of the Johnson House.
        - Harrison House, N.D. (Box 21, Folder 6)
          Photograph of the Harrison House with two individuals seated on the front porch.
        - Edmund Harrison House (Box 21, Folder 7)
          Photographs of the Edmund Harrison House and surrounding farm.
        - Harrison-Bradford Photograph, N.D. (Box 21, Folder 8)
          Photographs of the Harrison and Bradford houses pasted onto a sheet of paper. Paper includes genealogical information on John Rogers Harrison and John Bradford, both of whom were descended from "Mayflower" passengers.
        - Noah Harrison Barn, N.D. (Box 21, Folder 9)
          Photograph of a barn built by Noah Harrison. Harrison was a Revolutionary War veteran and the first member of the Harrison family to settle in Cornwall.
        - Hurlburt Garage, 1940, N.D. (Box 21, Folder 10)
          Photographs of an auto garage and filling station operated by the Hurlburt family. The building was torn down in 1940.
        - Palmer Mill, circa 1880, N.D. (Box 21, Folder 11)
          Photographs of the Palmer Mill. Images include the mill in operation and mill workers.
        - Prentice Barn, 1989 (Box 21, Folder 12)
          Photograph of the Prentice Barn along Lake Road.
        - Cornwall Hollow Road, N.D. (Box 21, Folder 13)
          Photograph of the Roberts Place on Great Hollow Road. The photo was given to the Cornwall Library in November 1943.
        - Hautboy Hill Road, N.D. (Box 21, Folder 15)
          Photographs of various properties along Hautboy Hill Road. Specific images include a photo of the birthplace of Major General John Sedgwick.
        - C. P. Smith House, N.D. (Box 21, Folder 16)
          Two photos of the C.P. Smith House along Hautboy Hill Road.
        - Carl Van Doren House (Box 21, Folder 17)
          Two photos of the Carl Van Doren House on Cream Hill Road.
        - Mark Van Doren House (Box 21, Folder 18)
          Two photographs of the Mark Van Doren House on Bradford Hill Road, one of which was taken by Emily E. Marsh.
        - Poised Rock, N.D. (Box 21, Folder 19)
          Photographs of the balancing boulders in Johnson Hollow, estimated to weigh approximately 100 tons.
        - Hurlburt Carriage House, 1941-circa 2000, N.D. (Box 21, Folder 20)
          Photographs of the Hurlburt family carriage house along Hurlburt Road.
        - General John Sedgwick House, N.D. (Box 21, Folder 21)
          Photographs of the Italiante style home of General John Sedgwick (1813-1864). The home is listed on the National Register of Historic Places.
        - Ford Hill Road, circa 2000 (Box 21, Folder 22)
          Two photographs of an unidentified home along Ford Hill Road.
        - Lake Road, N.D. (Box 21, Folder 23)
          Photographs of unidentified properties along Lake Road.
        - Route 43, N.D. (Box 21, Folder 24)
          Photographs of unidentified homes along Route 43, as well as images of the Sedgwick Monument.
        - Miscellaneous, 1919-circa 2000, N.D. (Box 21, Folder 26)
          Photographs of several unlabeled properties in Cornwall Hollow, as well as one image of lumber along the "Road by the Lake."
        - Fox House, N.D. (Box 37, Folder 13)
          Photograph of the former Fox family home. The house burned at an unknown date.
        - Waterfall at the Glen, N.D. (Box OS 3, Folder 10)
          Photograph of the "Waterfall at the Glen" taken by Mrs. John C. Kendall.
        - Waterfall at the Glen, N.D. (Box OS 3, Folder 11)
          Photograph of the 'Waterfall at the Glen" taken by Mrs. John C. Kendall.
      - West Cornwall
        - Post Offices, circa 1975-1989, N.D. (Box 21, Folder 27)
          Photographs of two post offices that stood in West Cornwall, including the current structure and an older building that is no longer extant.
        - J. Mallinson Shear Company, 1900, N.D. (Box 21, Folder 28)
          Photographs of the J. Mallinson Shear Company factory that stood along Lower River Road. Images include photos of the factory from various angles, as well as factory workers.
        - Chapel, 1942, N.D. (Box 21, Folder 29)
          Photographs of the West Cornwall Chapel. Photos include images of the building's interior and exterior.
        - The Bee Hive/ F.J. Bate Meat Market, 1989, N.D. (Box 21, Folder 30)
          Photographs of the building in West Cornwall that functioned first as a social hall known as the Bee Hive, and then later as Bate's Meat Market.
        - O'Donnell House, N.D. (Box 21, Folder 31)
          Photographs of the Patrick "Cap" O'Donnell House. The home was built in the 1870s and is alternately known as the "Rock Cottage."
        - Yutzler House, 1941, N.D. (Box 21, Folder 32)
          Photographs of the F.A. Yutzler House on River Road.
        - Eureka Mining Company, circa 1900 (Box 21, Folder 33)
          Two photographs a mine owned by the Eureka Mining Company. The company was based in Trenton, New Jersey and sought to extract feldspar from a deposit located about a half mile south of West Cornwall.
        - Tarradiddle Farm, 1940, N.D. (Box 21, Folder 34)
          Photographs of the Tarradiddle Farm in West Cornwall. Images include photos of the farm house and greenhouse.
        - Sturges House/ Wish House, N.D. (Box 21, Folder 35)
          Photographs of the building along Railroad Street currently known as the Wish House. There are photos of the structure, which dates to the 1840s, as both the Wish House and the private dwelling of the Sturges family.
        - Gannett House, N.D. (Box 21, Folder 36)
          Photographs of the home formerly owned by Michael Gannett on River Road.
        - River Road/ Lower River Road, 1920-1989, N.D. (Box 21, Folder 37)
          Photographs of various properties along River Road and Lower River Road. Specified houses include those owned by the Marsh, Flint, Gagnier, Opley, Fowler, and Weaton families. There are also images of the Estee Rubber Factory, which burned in the 1920s, Ian Ingersoll's Cabinetmaking Shop, and the home and forge owned by blacksmith William Oliver. There are additionally two photos of the railroad tracks in the area.
        - Foster House, 1989-circa 2000, N.D. (Box 21, Folder 38)
          Photographs of the Italiante style home originally owned by the Foster family. The building, also known as the "Pink House," later served as an inn.
        - Yutzler's Store, 1934-1995, N.D. (Box 21, Folder 39)
          Photographs of the store located along the Sharon-Goshen Turnpike formerly run by the Yutzler family. There are images of both the interior and exterior of the building, and of members of the Yutzler family working in the store.
        - St. Agnes Chapel, N.D. (Box 21, Folder 40)
          Photograph of the St. Agnes Chapel located on the grounds of the Trinity Conference Center on Lower River Road.
        - Sturges Stores, N.D. (Box 21, Folder 41)
          Photographs of two stores along the Sharon-Goshen Turnpike owned by the Sturges family. There is one image of a store run by Theo Sturges, which sold tin, plumbing, and heating accessories and was located across the street from the former Catholic church currently owned by Bain Real Estate. There are two photos of Sturges & Son, a general store that was located in the building currently occupied by Cornwall Bridge Pottery.
        - Route 7, 1941-circa 2000, N.D. (Box 21, Folder 42)
          Photographs of various buildings along Route 7. Specified images include properties owned by the Doolitte, Preston, Graham, Bates, Cochrane, and Schnider families. There are also several photos of the Housatonic Inn and of the construction of the route itself.
        - Fire House/ Ambulance Barn, 1976, N.D. (Box 21, Folder 43)
          Photographs of the West Cornwall fire house and ambulance barn. The fire house was built in 1932 by Lawrence Sturges.
        - Cartwright Garage, 1927-1938, N.D. (Box 21, Folder 44)
          Photographs of the garage along Route 7 operated by Edward Cartwright. The brick structure was built circa 1915 and served as both a filling station and automobile dealership.
        - Covered Bridge: Front View, 1929-1990, N.D. (Box 21, Folder 45)
          Photographs of the West Cornwall Covered Bridge taken from the frontal view.
        - Covered Bridge: Side Views, circa 1913-1989, N.D. (Box 22, Folder 1)
          Photographs of the West Cornwall Covered Bridge taken from various side views.
          - Covered Bridge, N.D. (Box OS 4, Object 2)
            Photograph of a team of horses and wagon crossing the covered bridge.
        - Covered Bridge: Aerial Views, N.D. (Box 22, Folder 2)
          Aerial views of the West Cornwall Covered Bridge
        - Covered Bridge: Interior Views, 1988 (Box 22, Folder 3)